<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Voyages &amp; travels of that renowned captain, Sir Francis Drake, into the West-Indies, and round the world giving a perfect relation of his strange adventures, and many wonderful discoveries, his fight with the Spaniard, and many barbarous nations : his taking St. Jago, St. Domingo, Carthagena, St. Augusta and many other places in the golden country of America, and other parts of the world : his description of monsters and monstrous people : with other other remarkable passages not before extant : containted in the history of his life and death, both pleasant and profitable to the reader.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65183</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12368247_60477</idno>
  <idno type="VID">60477</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248619643</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing V747</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1106</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12368247</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.  Navigations series.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65183)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60477)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 903:8 or 1078:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Voyages &amp; travels of that renowned captain, Sir Francis Drake, into the West-Indies, and round the world giving a perfect relation of his strange adventures, and many wonderful discoveries, his fight with the Spaniard, and many barbarous nations : his taking St. Jago, St. Domingo, Carthagena, St. Augusta and many other places in the golden country of America, and other parts of the world : his description of monsters and monstrous people : with other other remarkable passages not before extant : containted in the history of his life and death, both pleasant and profitable to the reader.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by C.B. for J.F., and sold by E. Tracy ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1652]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>This item appears at reels 903:8 and 1078:3.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Printing date taken from NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Drake, Francis, --  Sir, 1540?-1596.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Voyages and travels --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">West Indies --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60477:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Voyages &amp; Travels Of that Renowned Captain, <hi>Sir Francis Drake,</hi> INTO THE WEST-INDIES, AND Round about the WORLD:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Giving a perfect Relation of his strange Adventures, and many wonderful Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries, his Fight with the <hi>SPANIARD,</hi> and many barbarous Nations; his taking St. <hi>JAGO,</hi> St. <hi>DOMINGO, CARTHAGENA,</hi> St. <hi>AU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GUSTA,</hi> and many other Places in the Golden Country of <hi>AMERICA,</hi> and other Parts of the World: His Description of Monsters, and Monstrous Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. With many other remarkable Passages not before Extant: Contained in the History of his Life and Death; both pleasant and profitable to the Reader.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed by</hi> C. B. <hi>for</hi> J. F. <hi>and sold by</hi> E. Tracy, <hi>at the Three Bibles on</hi> London-bridge.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:60477:2"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Voyages and Travels of Sir <hi>Francis Drake.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SIr <hi>Francis Drake</hi> was born at <hi>Ipswich,</hi> and in his Youth put Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice to a Master of a Vessel, during which time he gave himself wholly to the study of Marine Affairs and grew so per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect therein, that he in the end became the World's Wonder, the Nation's Glory and Terror to his Enemies; in demonstration of which, I shall declare his several Voyages and great Atcheivements, till his Death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> Having by his many Exploits gained great Applause, and the Reputation of an able Sea-man, was made Captain of a small Vessel by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and imployed against the Spaniard, her mortal Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, from whom he took divers Prizes near Home; but not so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, he, on the 24th of <hi>May,</hi> 1575, set sail in the <hi>Paschal of Ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> a Ship of 70 Tuns, and mounted with 10 Guns, accompanied with the <hi>Swan,</hi> a Ship of 25 Tuns, and 8 Guns, commanded by his Brother <hi>John Drake;</hi> having on Bord both the Vessels, 73 Men and Boys, with other Necessaries, and having a fair Wind, came to <hi>Guadalupa,</hi> one of the <hi>West India</hi> Islands, on the 29th of <hi>June,</hi> but found nothing there, except some few Cottages made of Boughs, and covered with <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lmata</hi> Leaves, which secured them from Rain, in the Nature of Tiles yet they had sight of two <hi>Canows</hi> but could not reach them, by reason the Calm was so great. These <hi>Canows</hi> are Boats which the <hi>Indians</hi> use, being for the most part cut out of Trees like Troughs, and a piece of Wood fixed on either side, to keep them from overturn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Whereupon, after they had watered there, they weighed Anchor, and sailed to <hi>Port Phesant,</hi> so named, because of the abundance of that sort of Fowl found there; and there going on Shoar, found that one Mr. <hi>Garret</hi> of <hi>Plymouth</hi> had been lately there, and had left an Inscrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Lead nailed to a Tree, to warn him not to stay in that Port, forasmuch as the Spaniards had notice of his Arrival; yet landing more Forces, he resolved to stay and build a Pinnace, which he effected, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying the Port in the mean while, to prevent any Surprize. And whilst they stayed there, a Bark came from the <hi>Isle of Wight,</hi> bringing in a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Prize, which joyn'd with Capt. <hi>Drake;</hi> so that having finish'd the Pinnace, the 3 Ships and Pinnace sailed to the <hi>Isle of Pinos,</hi> where they found 2 Spanish Ships of <hi>Nombre de Dios,</hi> lading Timber by the Negroes. By those Vessels they were informed of the State of the City and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and that new Forces we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e daily expected, to defend it against the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60477:2"/> Symerons, a black People, with long Hair, who had revolted from the Spaniards, by reason of their Cruelty, and since chosen themselves two Kings. Whereupon setting the Negroes on Shoar with some gifts, Capt. <hi>Drake</hi> resolved to go to <hi>Nombre de Dios,</hi> which he entered by Night, beating the Spaniards from their Defences, who hung Lines a thwart the East-end of the Street, to make the <hi>English</hi> believe, by the lighted Matches tyed thereon, that their Forces were greater than indeed they were, and immediately fired, which was answered with a like num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Fire-shot and arrows from the English; they came to push of Pike, and Butt-end of the Musket, upon which the Spaniards fled, and the King's Treasury consisting of 360 Tun of Silver Bars, and a like Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of Gold, had fell into the Hands of the English, had not Capt. <hi>Drake</hi> been unfortunately wounded in the Leg, which caused the loss of so much Blood that he fainted; yet nevertheless he perswaded his Men to persist, for that the like Advantage could not be expected to be regained, if it was once omitted; but they preferring their Captain's Life before the Treasure, forced him on Ship-board. In this Battle only one <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> Man was killed, and three or four wounded by the Weapons the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy had cast away in their Flight; several of the Spaniards were kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and taken Prisoners. But Capt. <hi>Drake</hi> being now on Ship-board, and well perceiving the Spaniards had encreased their Forces, thought it not convenient with so small a Number, to make a second Attempt, therefore taking a Vessel laden with Wines, which at his coming he found in the Port, he set sail for the Port <hi>Plenty,</hi> and there, by the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of a Negro, carressed the Symerons found there, who being mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Enemies to the Spaniards, joyned friendship with him, and greatly furthered his Affairs: and sailing thence towards <hi>Carthagena,</hi> he took a great Ship richly laden, and after that another, in which were two of the Spanish King's <hi>Scrivendoes,</hi> who were sent from <hi>Nombre de Di s,</hi> with the News of what had hapne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there. Yet he acted not so secretly, but that his coming was known to the <hi>Cartagenians,</hi> who taking the Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, came dovvn to the Shoar in great numbers, insomuch that <hi>Drake</hi> thought it no vvays convenient to land there: And that his Pinnaces might be the better manned, he caused his great Ship to be sunk, after all things necessary vvere taken out of her, and sailed from that Port, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for some time undiscovered, about a League thence, and caused the Negroes to build Houses, to shelter his Men from the violent Storms of Rain that fell during his stay: To vvhich place the <hi>Indians</hi> brought store of Water and Victuals, for vvhich they vvere amply gratified. At vvhich
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60477:3"/> place leaving one Ship, he, with the two Pinnaces, sailed to <hi>Rio Grand,</hi> where roving up a great River, the Marriners were much afflicted with the insufferable stinging of Flyes, called <hi>Muskatos,</hi> against which there is no Remedy, but Juice of Lemons, with which the Skin being wet, they will not fasten. In the River he met two <hi>Indian Canows,</hi> in which were Fisher-men, but took no notice of them, for fear of being disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd, but passing for Spaniards, the Captain and his Men came to a Store-house on the River-side, where they found great plenty of Provision, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Fleet that was to return into <hi>Spain;</hi> after which, having notice that the Spaniards were coming down, they returned to their Pinnaces, and soon after took five or six small Barks laden with Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, setting the Men on Shoar, and so sailed to the Country of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merons, who kindly received them. These Symerons are a People inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting between <hi>Cabezas,</hi> and <hi>Rio-piego,</hi> who by certain Negroes, were given to understand, That <hi>Drake</hi> came as a Friend, and would protect them against the Attemps of the Spaniards; which caused them to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the English to confer with them, and furnish them with such Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessaries as they required; promising <hi>Drake,</hi> that as soon as the five rainy Months were past, in which the Spaniards never carry their Treasure by Land, they would so order the matter, that he should make himself Master of much Gold. Whereupon he ordered them to build him six Houses, for sheltering his Men, which they did, as likewise with the help of the English a Fort Triangle, which the Captain fortifyed to prevent any Surprize; and leaving part of his Men there, sailed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the pleasant Islands, in the River replenished with Gardens, and delicious Fruits, where the Indians were at his Devotion, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering up their Bows and Arrows, bringing Baskets of Fruit and Jui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Bails, as an Oblation of these People. <hi>Drake</hi> inquired into the State of the Country, and then sailed towards <hi>Charesha,</hi> and anchored between the Island, and the Main-land to defend which, the Spaniards had lined the Shoar vvith Shot, firing incessantly at the English, so that they vvere oblig'd to stand off, the Captain having one of his Men sore wounded; and next Morning took a Bark laden with Provision and Sweet-meats, bound for <hi>Cartagena,</hi> setting all the Men on Shoar, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a Negro, whom the Captain kept, to be by him instructed in the Affairs of the Country; and anchoring at the Mouth of the <hi>Haven</hi> of <hi>Cartagena,</hi> took two other Barks, which caused the Spaniards to send a <hi>Scrivaneo</hi> with a Flag of Truce, who desired to be admitted on Board, which was accordingly granted; But <hi>Drake</hi> finding his Message was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60477:3"/> to protract time, till the Forces came down to surprize him, would not accept of his Invitation on Shoar, which Treachery was soon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent. For the Spaniards perceiving <hi>Drake</hi>'s Wariness, and that they could not get him within their reach by Land, sent two Ships of War to fight him by Sea, which he perceiving, went joyfully to encounter them: But after the exchange of several shot, the Spaniards finding their Entertainment too warm, put themselves under the Protection of the Castle, and soon after came two other Pinnaces, who fared no better than the former: Whereupon <hi>Drake</hi> landed several of his Men, and drove the Spaniards from the Shoar, and for their Safety, to betake themselves some to the Town, and others to a thick Wood standing close by; but Victuals growing scarce, he was obliged to stand away to <hi>Rio Grand,</hi> where a little before he had found store of Provision, but now was frustrated in his Expectation, for the Spaniards had caused the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to retire to the Mountains, and carry away with them all their Cattle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But at length meeting with several small Vessels which he took, their Want was in some Measure supplyed, yet the Scarcity caused a Sickness to rage among the Marriners, but providence so or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered it, that only one of them dyed.</p>
               <p>The Sickness ended, <hi>Drake</hi> returned to the Fort, vvhere he had left part of his Men, together vvith the Symerons; but upon his arrival; to his great Grief, found his Brother, and one <hi>Richard Allen,</hi> dead of the Wounds they received in attempting to Board a Spanish Ship of considerable Force. Nor was this all the Loss, for <hi>Joseph Drake,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Captains Brothers, soon after dyed of a Calenture; yet he took Courage, and being supplyed by the Symerons, he attended his better Fortune, and vvas soon after informed by those People (vvho like Grey-hounds ranged the Country to learn vvhat they could) that the Spanish Fleet vvas arrived at <hi>Nombre de Dios;</hi> vvhereupon <hi>Drake</hi> sent the <hi>Lyon</hi> Frigat to descry them, vvho upon her approaching that Port fell in vvith a small Spanish Vessel laden vvith Mace, Hens, and Pompi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, from <hi>Tolon.</hi> The Spaniards that vvere found therein, the Captain used courteously, protecting them from the Fury of the Symerons, vvho are mortal Enemies to the Spaniards.</p>
               <p>Upon certain notice that the Fleet vvas arrived, <hi>Drake</hi> conferred vvith the native Symerons, about the Necessaries that vvere to be provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the Expedition, to surprize such Carriages of Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, as vvere to come over Land; vvho told him he must be vvell fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished vvith Weapons and Shooes, and that for the rest they would not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60477:4"/> be wanting; which being provided, 48 Men set forward, of which, 30 were Symerons, and the rest English; the former serving instead of Sumpeteres for carrying Provision, and when the store failed, they would range the Woods, and catch such Provision as they could, sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom missing to return without a Buck or Faun, or store of Foul, bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about them many Arrows, headed with Iron, Wood, or Fishes Bones; which they will cast so dexterously, that they seldom miss the Iron, with which their Arrows are headed, and is frequently found to be more precious in their Estimation than Gold.</p>
               <p>This March they continued over Land through many thick Woods, from Sun-rise, till ten in the Morning, and then resting in watery plaaes till four in the Afternoon, they walked till eight; and when Darkness came on, the Symerons laying aside their Burthens, would cut down Boughs to build Harbours with, covering them to keep out the Rain, if any should fall, building them with <hi>Planata</hi> Leaves, decent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise according to the Fashion of <hi>Norway</hi> Cottages; insomuch that no Rain would enter for the space of 24 Hours; nor were they wanting to bring several sorts of Fruits, as <hi>Mammeas, Guyanas, Palmitos, Pinos, Oranges, Lemons,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>After three Days travel, they came to a Town of Symerons, situate on a Hill near a River, composed with a Dike of eight Foot broad, and a thick Mud-wall ten Foot in height, containing one broad Street from East to West, and two cross Streets of a lesser breadth; all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting of sixty Families, who in their Apparel, somewhat imitated the Spaniards: This Town is distant from <hi>Nombre de Dios</hi> 35 Leagues, and 45 from <hi>Panama,</hi> being sufficiently stored with all manner of Plenty. As for their Religion, they have no Priests, yet they hold Crosses in great Veneration; but at the Perswasion of the English they laid their Crosses aside, and in some measure embrace the Worship of the true God, learning the <hi>Lord's-Prayer,</hi> and many other necessary Articles of Belief; they continually were upon their Guard, for fear of the Spaniards, who daily molested them, aiming at the Subversion of that Place, on which they made several Attempts, but without Success, their Scouts upon the Frontiers continually giving notice of their approach, and so alarumed their neighbouring Towns, especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that wherein the King resided, in which were supposed to be 1700 fighting Men; and fain would they have entreated the Captain to a long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Residence amongst them, but he being intent on his Journey, with many Expressions of Kindness took his leave, and so marching with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60477:4"/> four Symerons, who knew the way about a Mile before him, who by breaking off Boughs, and strewing them in the way, gave Directions; and the other twenty four divided equally for his Vaunt-guard, and Rear-guard, the English continuing in the middle. After passing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny gloomy Woods, which shelter'd them from the Sun's hot Beams, they came to a great Hill, on which stood a high Tree, in which were cut several Steps, that led to a pleasant Bower, situate on the top, in which, ten or twelve Men might sit, and from thence take a View of the North and South <hi>Atlantick</hi> Ocean; and from thence they passed on to a plain Champain Country, abounding in Grass so high, that the Inhabitants are obliged to burn it twice or thrice a Year, to give their Cattle advantage of feeding; through which they travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to <hi>Panama,</hi> and for fear of being discovered, struck through a gloomy Grove, on the right Hand, and at the Edge thereof resting, they sent a Symeron disguised like a Negro, to <hi>Panama,</hi> to enquire what Night, for by Day they travelled not, by reason of the heat of the Sun, the <hi>Recoes</hi> passed to <hi>Venta Cruz,</hi> in order to their Passage to <hi>Nombre de Dios,</hi> to land the Fleet, and by him, upon his return had notice, That that Night eight Mules laden with Gold and Silver, and one with Jewels, together with fifty others laden with Provisions and Merchandize, were to pass the Road; whereupon <hi>Drake,</hi> with his Men, and the Symerons, placed themselves in the Grass, and thick Shrubs, near to the Way-side, in expectation of the rich Booty: The Truth of which was likewise confirmed by a Spanish Soldier, taken by two Symerons, and brought to the Captain; and so placed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, that whilst one Party was seizing on the foremost Mules, the other might take the hinder-most. And all things had succeeded to their Wish, had not an English Man and a Symeron, though contrary to the strict Command of the Captain, suddenly started out to seize a Cavalier coming from <hi>Venta-Cruz,</hi> who perceiving them by the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Man's white Shirt, which he and the rest had put over his Cloaths, the better to distinguish them if it should come to a Skirmish, as in all likelyhood it would, he suddenly put Spurs to his Horse, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stripped them; about a League distance meeting with the <hi>Recoes,</hi> he informed the Conveyors of what he had seen, tell ng them, that he was sure that either <hi>Drake,</hi> or some of his Men, lay in Ambush for them; So the <hi>Reooes,</hi> laden with Gold and Silver, and Jewels, turned back again, only that laden with Provision, Merchandize, and a small quantity of Treasure, come forward, which was accordingly taken,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60477:5"/> and declared the manner of the Prevention; imploring <hi>Drake</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them from the Rage of the Symerons.</p>
               <p>Matters being at this pass, it was not thought safe to stay in those parts, but to return to their Ships, which they could not do, but by the tedious way they came, or by cutting their way through <hi>Venta-cruz,</hi> the latter of which was less difficult, <hi>Drake</hi> resolved on, and therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding his Men to refresh themselves, asked <hi>Pedro,</hi> Captain of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merons, whether he would stand by him or no? Who answered, he would dye at his Feet, e're he would leave him; and thereupon on they marched till they came near the Town, and there taking out of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coes what was best Portable, they turned back the Mules and their Dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, commanding them on pain of Death, not to follow them; and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the way, cut through a thick Wood, as thick as our English Hedges, they were encountered by a Company of Spaniards, under the leading of a Convent Fryer; when after a hot Skirmish (in which <hi>John Harris,</hi> an English Man, and one <hi>Symeron</hi> were killed) the Spaniards were put to Flight, many of them being killed, wounded, and taken Prisoners; the Symerons at that time behaving themselves valiantly, doing with their Arrows great Execution. But far they had not marched e're the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, who had retired, being reinforced, had fortify'd themselves in a Wood, by which the English must pass; into which Wood the Symerons in a dancing Posture rushed, singing in their Tone, <hi>Yo-peho, Yo-peho,</hi> and with their Arrows drove the poor <hi>Spaniards</hi> thence, with the loss of but one Man; who, wounded as he was, e're he dyed, killed two Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards.</p>
               <p>The Out-guards beaten, those that remained in the Town made but small Resistance, so that the English and Symerons entring, found most of their Houses abandoned. This Town of <hi>Venta-cruz,</hi> consists not of above fifty Houses, besides one Monastery, and a few Store-houses. Here likewise they found three Spanish Gentlewomen that had lately been delivered of Children came some Days before from <hi>Nombre de Dios;</hi> for that it had been observed, that no Spaniard, or White, had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been delivered at the latter place, but that the Child soon after dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: But that being brought to Bed at <hi>Venta-cruz,</hi> or any other place adjacent, the Children came to Maturity. In Compassion of this, <hi>Drake</hi> strictly commanded, that neither his own Men or the Symerons, should Out-rage them: And so having set a Guard upon all the Passes, they took some small Pillage and departed, having first beaten back twelve Horse-men, who supposing them gome, came thither from <hi>Panama.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:60477:5"/>
               <p>Thus the chief Ends, for which the Journey was undertaken, being unluckily frustrated, <hi>Drake</hi> (after a tedious March, in which many of his Men had perished by Hunger and Thirst, had not the Symerons pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved their Purveyors) arrived to his Ships; those on Board, who before were in great Heaviness for his Absence, abundantly rejoycing at his return; and so staying on Board in the River <hi>Fortugos,</hi> for some time a Consult was held, what Enterprize was next to be undertaken; in which the Opinion of the Symerons was held necessary, as they who best knew the Country, and where the Treasure lay; who gave Council, that near a Town called <hi>Varagna,</hi> lived one <hi>Senior Pezero,</hi> who had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been Master to some of them, and whom for his Cruelty they had abandoned; and that this Man, in a strong Store-house, guarded by a 100 Slaves, had heaped up great Treasure, being Proprietor of several rich Mines. This Advice pleased them, yet they were prevented at that time by another Advice; for one of the Frigats being abroad, had taken a small Spanish Prize, in which was a <hi>Genoway</hi> Pilot; the said Pilot, upon his being kindly entreated, informed <hi>Drake,</hi> that in the <hi>Bay</hi> of <hi>Vicarague,</hi> lay a Vessel ready to depart, in which was a Million of Gold, and that by his Knowledge of the Channel, if he might partake in the Gains, he could bring him in undiscovered, and that he might have time to dispatch his business, e're the Town could be allarum'd. Whereupon the Captain giving such of the Symerons (who were willing thereto) leave to depart, giving them many large Gifts, he took the rest with their Captain on Board, and set sail on this so-much-desired Prize; but entering the Harbour, altho' it was not yet dark, he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood by the firing of several Chambers, which were answered by others a distance thence, that he was discovered, and the Wind turning against him, he thought it not fit to attempt any thing further in the matter. So returning to his Station, he met the <hi>Bear</hi> Frigat, a small Vessell that he had fitted up, who had taken a Spanish Bark, laden with twenty fat Hogs, two hundred Hens, and great store of Mace; which is a kind of Grain like Rice, and in it ten Spaniards, who informed him, that the Fleet was arrived at <hi>Nombre de Dios,</hi> and that two Gallies were building there to waft them to and fro, but not yet lanced. Whereupon <hi>Drake</hi> feasting his Men in this manner on <hi>Easter-day,</hi> which that Year fell on the twentieth of <hi>March,</hi> he resolved to attempt something on the Fleet, and weighing Anchor, bore with the Wind, till at length they espyed a small Vessel plying to the West-ward, which after some sailing. was discryed to be a French Vessel; whose Captain likewise supposing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60477:6"/> it was <hi>Drake,</hi> stood with him, and in a most submssive manner, he beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged some fresh Water, for that he had nothing but Wine and Cider on Board; the which, by reason of the hot Weather, had much impaired the Health of his Men with which <hi>Drake</hi> supplyed him, willing to stand with him to the next Port, which he accordingly did, making him there a Present of a Case of Pistols, and a Gilt Scimeter, which he said had been the late King of <hi>France</hi>'s, who was killed in Just with <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur de Gomery;</hi> in requital of which, <hi>Drake</hi> gave him a Chain of Gold, and a further Supply of necessary Provision. So that in the end he was willing to accompany him in his Voyage and take such part as should befal him; yet <hi>Drake</hi> not altogether satisfied in his Fidelity, so divided either Nation, that it was not in the Power of the <hi>French</hi> Men, if they would, to have injured the English; and then sending for the Symeron Captain, he approved of what was done, and thereupon it was agreed, that twenty French, fifteen English, and a considerable number of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merons, should pass over Land, to intercept the Ricoes that were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from <hi>Panama,</hi> to <hi>Nombre de Dios,</hi> when having gone seven Leagues, the Bells of the Camels and Mules were heard, which made the Syme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons rejoyce, assuring Capt. <hi>Drake,</hi> that he should have more Gold and Silver, than he could dispose of; and so indeed it fortuned, for the Ricoes being seized, a rich Booty appeared; but there being a Guard of forty Spaniards attending it, a hot Dispute hapned; but in the end, the Spaniards were put to Flight, and the Gold and Silver unladed, and every one took what he could conveniently carry; but scarce had they hid the rest, and entered the Wood, e're a great number of Horse and Foot came on, yet they kept their way, all escaping, except on Syme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron that was killed, and a French Soldier that was taken Prisoner, who being put to the Torture, confessed where the Gold was hid; in the Conflict the French Captain was dangerously wounded: But what was most amazing, was, that when they came to the Sea-side, where the Pinnaces had order to attend them, they perceived seven Spanish Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces, which were sent to take the English Vessels, then but weakly manned, whom <hi>Drake</hi> and the rest imagined to have executed their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign; but taking Courge, he resolved to make a Raft of such Trees as were driven on Shoor, and put to Sea, in order to seek his Vessels, which he accordingly put in practice, accompanied with one English Man, two French Men, and two Symerons, with a great joy found the Vessels safe, riding it out behind the Point and in spite of the Spaniards, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Promise, fetched o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> his Companions, when having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freshed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60477:6"/> themselves, they went to look for the hidden Treasure, but found as aforesaid, that the Spaniards, by the French Captain's Confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, had discovered it. Yet had they not searched so narrowly, but that they had left several Bars of Silver behind them, as also some Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its of Gold; but what troubled the French Men most, their Captain sore wounded as he was, fell into the Hands of the Spaniards, yet upon sharing the Booty equally amongst them and the English, they were comforted, especially upon the Arrival of one of their Companions, who had escaped the Hands of the Spaniards. Yet being desirous to depart into their own Country, they left the English, yet fearing the Danger they might incur, by falling into the Hands of the Spaniards, they repented their Rashness, and lingered till <hi>Drake</hi> overtook them: When notice being had that the Spanish Fleet richly laden were about to depart from <hi>Carthagena, Drake</hi> sailed to the Mouth of the Harbour, and there dropping his Anchor, braved them with all Streamers flying, and Flag astern, and took a Frigat of fifty Tuns, laden with Provision, within sight of 'em, and not to be cumbered with the Men taken there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, set them on Shoar, and so without longer stay sailed to <hi>Cabezas,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving first burnt the Ship, that it might no more advantage the Spaniards.</p>
               <p>During <hi>Drake</hi>'s Stay at <hi>Cabezas, Pedro,</hi> the Captain of the Symerons, importun'd him for certain Iron Instruments belonging to Navigation, which he frankly gave him for the good Service he had done for him: further promising that he would look out some Silk and Linnen for his Wife, not intending to hold any thing from him that he could conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently spare. But whilst he was looking in his Chest, the <hi>Indian</hi> espyed the Scimeter, given him by the French Captain, and was greatly desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of it, but being bashful himself, he gave another a Quoit of Gold to ask for it; and having his Request granted, he gave <hi>Drake</hi> four Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its of Gold in requital, saying, He would present it to his King, who would highly promote him for such a Present.</p>
               <p>And now <hi>Drake</hi> being desirous to return into <hi>England,</hi> rewarded the <hi>Symerons</hi> with divers Giefts, and after leave taken, tho' to the great Grief of those <hi>Indians,</hi> who earnestly desired the Company of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish,</hi> they stood away to the Island that bespangled the Ocean, and coast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Tract, came to the Cape St. <hi>Anthony,</hi> where they took two hundred and fifty Turtles, which they powdered and eat, as occasion required; and from thence sailing North-west, after touching at seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral places, they, to the great Joy of their Friends, who concluded them lost, arrived safe at <hi>Plymouth,</hi> on the 9th Day of <hi>June,</hi> 1573, bringing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60477:7"/> home to the Value of 80000 Pounds in Gold and Silver, and other Merchandize, besides the great Credit and Applause they obtained of all that heard of their strange Adventures. <hi>Drake</hi> himself being Knighted, and the rest amply rewarded.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sir <hi>Francis Drake,</hi> his Second Voyage, in which he compassed the World: In which is comprehended the many strange and wonderful Discoveries he made, during that extraordinary Navigation.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DRake</hi> impatient of remaining at Shoar, importuned his Soveraign Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that he might be Commissioned to make a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Voyage, the which after some Delays, was granted; whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Adventurers furnished him with five Ships, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Pelican</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable, burthened 100 Tuns, in which he imbarqued himself; The <hi>Elizabeth Vice-Admirable,</hi> Commanded by Capt. <hi>Joseph Winter,</hi> being a Ship of 80 Tuns; The <hi>Marrygold,</hi> a bark of 30 Tuns; Capt. <hi>John Thomas</hi> Commander; The <hi>Swan,</hi> a Fly-boat of 50 Tuns, <hi>John Chester</hi> Commander, and a small a Pinnace of 15 Tuns.</p>
               <p>These Vessels being manned with 164 able Seamen, and Soldiers, and furnished with all things necessary, sailed out of <hi>Plymouth</hi> Road on the 15th of <hi>November,</hi> 1577; yet met with many Difficulties, by reason of Tempests, and contrary Winds, e're they could get clear of the Land's End; at what time sailing towards the Coast of <hi>Barbary,</hi> they came to an Anchor on the Coast of <hi>Magadore,</hi> lying three Degrees, forty Minutes, being part of the Territories of the King of <hi>Fez,</hi> being a small Island not above three Leagues in Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference, abounding with Foul and Fish, though of an unusual Shape. There some of the English going on Shoar, the Negroes, who inhabit that place, were desirous to be conducted on board, for whose Security <hi>Drake</hi> left a Pledge on shoar, the Moors seemingly desiring to Traffick for such Commodities as the English had, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Sea-side, Camels laden with Merchandizes. But when the Negroes were returned, some of the English going on shoar in a boat, one of them, named <hi>John Fry,</hi> was detained, which much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>censed <hi>Drake,</hi> so that he was about to revenge the Indignity, to that Purpose landing his Men: But when he understood no Injury was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered him, they departed, and altho' he went not with them, yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Governour of that Island understood of what Nation he was, he sent him home in an English Ship, having upon his causing him to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60477:7"/> be surprized, conjectured him a <hi>Portugal,</hi> and that <hi>Drake</hi> was the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of the <hi>Portugal</hi> Fleet, preparing to indamage that Coast.</p>
               <p>Departing from this Island, <hi>Drake</hi> took a small <hi>Spanish</hi> Fisher-boat conducted but with three Men only; and after that, sailing under the <hi>Tropick Cancer,</hi> fell in with a Spanish Caravel, which he took, and then sailing to <hi>Cape Barbas,</hi> he there took another, though indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently laden with Provision; where having plenty of all things neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, he stayed a while, during which space, the Natives came down to view the English, bringing with them a <hi>Negro</hi> Woman half starved, with a Child at her Breast, offering her to sale, but <hi>Drake</hi> would not traffick for such Commodities; whereupon they brought Gums, and Amber-greese, offering it for fresh Water, which above all things is most scarce in that Country. Water they had, but <hi>Drake</hi> would not take any thing for the common Element, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise some Provision, for which they were very thankful for, eating greedily.</p>
               <p>Having thus far proceeded, they set the Spaniards on Shoar, and after trimming their Ship, sailed to <hi>Cape de Verde,</hi> and so coasted <hi>Bomavista,</hi> falling in with the <hi>Isle of Mayo,</hi> inhabited by the <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guese,</hi> and so touching at several Islands, came to St. <hi>Jago,</hi> on the South-West of which Island, they took a <hi>Portuguese</hi> Vessel, laden with Wine, Woollen, and Linnen-Cloath, on its return from <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zil,</hi> and in Defiance of those on Land, fired <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon three or four of their Towns, standing on the Sea-coast.</p>
               <p>Near to the Island of St. <hi>Jago,</hi> is the burning Island called <hi>Fogo,</hi> continually up casting Flames; and near to that, lies a pleasant Island, always clad with green, exceeding fruitful, abounding especially with Figs, Cocos, Planatoes, Oranges and Lemons; it is also repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished with pleasant Streams, though the Harbours about it, are not capable of receiving any Ships of Burthen: and in all the Island, was only one House supposed to be inhabited by an Hermet.</p>
               <p>From this Island, after having taken some of what it afforded, they stood away to the Coast of <hi>Brazil,</hi> but by contrary Winds were kept out so long at Sea, that Provision grew scanty, and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Water, which in that burning Climate was most requisite. But when they despaired of obtaining any, God so ordered it, that there fell great store of Rain, which supplyed their Necessity: And amongst many other strange Creatures found in those Seas, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60477:8"/> themselves with viewing the flying Fishes, which are as big as ordinary <hi>Pilchards,</hi> having Fins the length of their Bodies, so that when they are pursued by any Fish, and fear to be devoured, they save themselves by leaving their Element, and flying in the Air; but cannot continue it long, for that their Fins wanting moisture become unser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable, by reason of the thin Film that Joyns the Bones, or Quill, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Sailing from thence to the Coast of <hi>Brazil,</hi> they beheld huge Fires on the Shoar, made by the Inhabitants, in which they sacrificed two De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, using many Conjurations to raise Whirlwinds and Tempests, thereby to wreck such as approached their Coast: Which Hellish In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantations, the <hi>Portugals</hi> to their cost found fatal, when they first dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered those Countries; But the Engllsh sustained no other Dammage than the Separation of their Ships, when leaving that Coast altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rocky and inaccessible, <hi>Drake</hi> stood away to another Point, which he called <hi>Cape Joy,</hi> by reason he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re met the Ship he lost in the Storm, and having Watered and refreshed his Men at <hi>Cape Verd,</hi> and taken store of Deer, which that Country affords in abundance, he stood away twelve Leagues from the Main to a convenient Harbour, sheltering from the South-wind; and North-winter growing fast upon him, he sought out a Harbour where he might ride safe: and at last coming to <hi>Cape Hope,</hi> he entered with a Shallop, to sound the Bay, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised good Anchorage. But e're he could return so great a Fog arose, that he could not see the Ships, and a Storm withal arising, he was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endanged to be lost: But Captain <hi>Thomas,</hi> suspecting some Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger had befallen him by reason of his stay, entered with his Ship, and by firing a Gun, directed him to the Vessel, and having not yet received him on Board, dropped Anchor, and there lay till the Storm was over: And the next Day going on Shoar, made great Fires, as a Sign to the dispersed Ships to return into the Haven, who all met, except the <hi>Swan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon their landing the People fled, they entred a homely House near a Rock, where they found fifty Estriches of a Prodigious size, whose Weight were such, that they could not fly, but run as fast as Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hounds, so that they are not catched, but by decoying them into a Net, by the likeness of an Estrich made of their Feathers. <hi>Drake</hi> not find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Harbour for his Purpose, stood away South-west, about twelve Leagues, where entering a Port, a great number of the Natives pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented themselves upon a Hill, leaping and dancing after an extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant manner, and at first landing seemed fearful of the English, but soon
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60477:8"/> after became more familiar, bringing Estriches-feathers and Bones, variously carved and Arrows of Reed, which they delivered for Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Commodities. They went all naked, except a skin of Fur cast o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their Shoulders when they sit in the cold, but when they are doing any thing, they gird it about their Waste: Their Hair is long, which when they travel, they bind it up with Estriches Feathers, of which likewise they make thir Quivers. Their Bodies are painted with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Colours, and their Faces they wash with Sulphur: Upon them appear the Figures of Suns, Moons, and Stars, which they term the Marks and Characters of their Gods. Their Victuals is Roots, and Wild Beasts-flesh, which they eat raw; they have no Boats; and sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom enter the Water? those that appeared, were fifty in number; they use for their Weapons, Boms headed with Bone, and Flint-stones, artificially cut.</p>
               <p>Having stayed some time with these People, and caught in the Bay about 200 Seals, they weighed Anchor, and stood towards the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tartick Pole,</hi> till they ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to St. <hi>Julian,</hi> so named by <hi>Magelen,</hi> otherwise the Land of <hi>Gyants;</hi> for here are found People of a mighty Size, who at first received several of the English kindly, but in the end seeing their Advantage, killed one, and wounded two or three others, e're they could recover their Boat, yet not without the fall of two or three of their own Men, especi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lly of him who first began the Mischief, which Injury, <hi>Drake</hi> resolved to revenge. But upon their repenting what they had done, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring they supposed his Men to be Spaniards, who had slain many of their People, he departed that Coast, and soon after had notice of a Conspiracy against himself, and his Principal Captains, by one on Board: of which the Conspirator being detected, was wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily executed, worse Execution being thereby prevented. And so keeping on, came to three Islands lying Triangle-wise, which he called <hi>Elizabethides,</hi> in Honour of our Virgin Queen; On one of them he found store of Birds, as big as Stubble-geese, without Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, being only matted down on their Backs, and Beaks like a Crow: they cannot run fast, but swim exceeding swift; they lay their Eggs in the Ground, where they make Holes with their Beaks like Conies. Of these they killed 3000, and with them made mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: and then coming to another Island, inhabited by People of little Stature, he found them Rowing in Canows, made of the Bark of a Tree; But that place affording no Variety, he stood away to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60477:9"/> the South-Sea, sailing amongst the Islands 150 Leagues: but a Storm arising, his Fleet separated, and some Ships lost their Anchors, narrowly escaping the devouring Waves. But God so ordered it, that entering <hi>Mare Delzur,</hi> they got under the Tempest, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained safe till the Storm was over: and then stearing North-ward along the Coast of <hi>Peru,</hi> they entered an Island full of birds, inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited by Spaniards, and Native <hi>Indians;</hi> and being fallen with the Land, they sailed along the Coast two Degrees, where going on Shoar, the Natives at first received them kindly, and offer'd to Traffick with them: but having trained them into Danger, shot at them, as they were in their boat, killing and wounding divers others, as amongst which <hi>Drake</hi> was one, having an Arrow shot into his Nose, and another hit him on the Fore-head, yet he valuing not the loss of his Men, worth a hundred of theirs, thought not fit to go on Shoar to revenge the Injury. These People inhabiting the Islands, are such as the Cruelty of the Spaniards had driven from the Main, which Cruelty renders them unhospitable to all Strangers. Their Weapons are Spears, and Darts of Reed, headed with Stone and Bone.</p>
               <p>These harbrous People thus left, they not far distant, found an <hi>Indian</hi> Fishing in his <hi>Canow,</hi> who being taken, and brought on Board, was courteously entertained: who in Requital thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing set on Shoar, returned with divers others, bringing store of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision, and directed the English to a Watering-place, of which at that time they stood in great need; and soon after the Governour of the Country came on board, and they afterwards going on Shoar with him, found store of <hi>Chinly</hi> Wine, and other Rarities, in a homely Town, consisting mostly of Ware-houses.</p>
               <p>Being thus refreshed, <hi>Drake</hi> saild to seek the Ship separated from him in the Storm, carrying with him an <hi>Indian Pilot,</hi> the better to know those Seas, and stood away towards the Line; and by the way, putting into a convenient Harbour, built a Pinnace, and then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering a Bay South-ward, came to the Town of <hi>Cyppo,</hi> inhabited by the Spaniards, who discovering them e're they could Land any consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable number of Men, came down with 100 Spanish Horse, and 200 Indians on foot, running after them like Dogs. But e're they could prevent it, all but one Man was got on board, but he, bolder then the rest staying to out-face them in a bravery, was shot by one of them, and then by the <hi>Indians,</hi> stuck full of Arrows made of green Wood,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60477:9"/> cutting off his Head, and right Hand, and pulling out his Heart: yet what they left of him, his Companions came the next Day land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, buried. And leaving these butcherly Spaniards, sailing North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, they came to the Cape of <hi>Mormorena,</hi> where finding four In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians in their Canows, they promised to bring them to a place where they might Water, which accordingly they did, where lighting on a Spaniard a sleep, with thirteen Bars of Silver weighing 4000 Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Duckates, they eased him of the Burden: and not far from thence they met another Spaniard, and an Indian Boy, driving four <hi>Perva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Sheep, each Sheep bearing two bags, in each of which was fifty Pound weight of silver, which became likewise their Prize, and so returned on board: and a little from thence, met several <hi>Indians</hi> row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Boats of Leather sowed together, with these they carryed Knives and Glass Beads, for Fish.</p>
               <p>Sailing along the Tract, they came to another Island, near the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Cusco,</hi> where they found Sheep as big as Cows, whom the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants use in carrying their Burthens, the Wool and Flesh of which are excellent Cloathing and Provision. This Coast inhabited by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> which made our Men hope for some rich Booty, nor were they deceived in their Expectation; for the first thing they happened on, was a Bark with forty odd Bars of Silver, and soon after another laden with Linnen, and so sailed to <hi>Lima,</hi> 12 Degrees, 30 Minutes South-latitude, where they Anchored, although in the Harbour were 30 <hi>Spanish</hi> Vessels, boarding a Vessel that had in her 15000 Bars of Silver, of which, and some other Commodities found there, they ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed her: And having notice of a rich Ship, bound for <hi>Panama,</hi> they set sail, and falling with <hi>Francisco,</hi> about Noon they discovered her, and bearing up without Resistance boarded her, finding in her Fruits, Conserves, Sugars, and a great quantity of Jewels, 13 Chests of Plate Rial, 80 <hi>l.</hi> weight of Gold; and 26 Tun of uncoyned Silver, valued at 360000 Pezoes, for which they only gave the Master a little Linnen in Exchange, which he took, supposing that better than nothing, as well knowing <hi>Drake</hi> would be his own Carver.</p>
               <p>Sailing from thence one Degree, North Latitude, they met with a Ship laden with Linnen, and China Dishes; and besides found in it a <hi>Paulcon,</hi> with a great Emrald in its Breast, which they took, and so passed by the Port of <hi>Papagaia,</hi> and divers dangerous Gulphs, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually sending forth violent Winds. And entering the Port of <hi>Guaia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio,</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:60477:10"/> inhabited by the Spaniards, they furnished them with all things necessary, and compounded for their Safety, with a Pot of <hi>Riats,</hi> as big as a b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>shel, a Gold Chain, and a Jewel, whence sailing 500 Leagues, they came under sixty Degrees North Latitude, where, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it was about the middle of <hi>June,</hi> they were so afflicted with Cold. that they were obliged to haste thence, to save their Lives, all the Countries round being covered with Snow, and the Seas with Globes of Ice; so that sailing South-ward to thirty eight Degrees, the Weather was very temperate, where bearing with the Land, the Natives sent a Man in a Cannow, to invite them on shoar, who made a long Oration in his own Country Language, and by his Gestures, expressed his meaning, and being dismissed, he came again; and the third time bringing Presents of Estrich Feathers, which none but those about their Kingdom are suffered to wear, he brought also a basket filled with Herbs, called <hi>Taback,</hi> in Requital of which, <hi>Drake</hi> preffered him many things, but he would receive nothing but a Hat.</p>
               <p>Upon this Invitation <hi>Drake</hi> put to shoar, and landed his Men, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected a Tent, and armed it well, to prevent any Danger, if the Natives should prove Treacherous, who no sooner perceiving the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish come forth of their Ships, but they came down with great haste from the Hill, and fell down at their Feet, worshipping them as Gods, throwing away their Bows and Arrows, and made many Laments and Cries.</p>
               <p>These People <hi>Drake</hi> treated courteously, bestowing shirts, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things upon them, wherewith to cover their Nakedness; signify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto them, that he was but a Man, and that all his Company were Mortals, and no Gods, as these poor deluded People supposed them to be; to the belief of which they could hardly perswade them. In Recompence of what they had received, they bestowed upon the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Bows, Quivers of their Arrows, and the like; and so with Joy, which they expressed by their leaping and Dancing, they departed to their Houses, which they digged round into the Earth, having Chests of Wood set up, and joyned close at the top like a Spire, without Chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys. Their Door is like an ordinary Scuttle in a Ship, sloap wise; their Men for the most part go naked, being of a loving and tractable Nature: their only Weapons are Bows and Arrows, with which, though they are Skilful, they do but little Execution, they being of no Force: Their Women make themselves loose Garments of bulrush<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, to cover their Secrets, wearing on their Shoulders beasts skins, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing altogether obedient to their Husbands.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:60477:10"/>
               <p>Two Days after, a great Multitude of them came down to the Tent, leaving their Women and bows some distance behind them, upon a Hill; who as soon as they were arrived at the Tent, fell to scratch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Faces, and casting themselves upon the Ground, with lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table cries, as they use to do when they offer Sacrifice to their Gods, not being yet perswaded but that the English were such, though <hi>Drake</hi> and his Company, endeavoured to undeceive them, with pointing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven, Praying, and singing Psalms.</p>
               <p>Three Days after their King came down, attended by a great number, who sung in a lamentable Tone about him; before him one bore a Scepter, made of black Wood, about a yard and half long, whereon hanged three Crowns, two Chains, and a bag of Herbs, called <hi>Tabak;</hi> the King had on a Caul of Net-work, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembling a Crown on his Shoulders, and his Waste a Coat of Coney-skins; his Guards had Coats of other Skins, and Cauls with Feathers in them, of divers Colours, or covers with down, which grroweth on a Herb like a Lettice, which Down is not permitted to be worn, but by those about the King, the Seed of it is only used in Sacrifice to their Gods. The common sort were for the most part naked, with long Hair, tyed with bunches of Feathers, every one having their Faces painted. Lastly, The Women came with Baskets on their Arms, made of Rushes, so closely Woven, that they would hold Water, being hanged with Pearl-shells, and other shells, and with two or three links of a Chain, signifying they were Vessels dedicated to their Gods. He that bore the Scepter, made an Oration for the space of half an hour, which ended with a general <hi>Amen,</hi> and all (save the Children) came down the Hill.</p>
               <p>Being come near, he that bore the Scepter, with a stately Carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age began a Song, and a Dance, as also did the King and all the rest (save the Women) who daunced, but did not sing. Which ended, they entered the Tent, where the King caused his Crown to be set upon <hi>Drake</hi>'s Head, desiring him, which by many Signs he made to take upon him the Kingdom, saluting him by the Name of <hi>Hyoh,</hi> ending the Solemnity with a Song and a Dance, which <hi>Drake</hi> received, to the behoof of her Majesty. When as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People leaving the King with <hi>Drake,</hi> went amongst the rest of the English, and finding such as pleased their Fancies, which were commonly the Youngest, and most beautiful, they inclosed them
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60477:11"/> round, and offered Sacrifices to them, crying with lamentable Shricks, weeping, scratching, and tearing their Flesh from off their Faces.</p>
               <p>This Country abounding with all things necessary for the Use of Man, <hi>Drake</hi> named <hi>Albion,</hi> and at his departure, set up her Majesty's Picture and Title to the Kingdom, ingraven in Brass. Loath were these People, that the <hi>English</hi> should forsake them, and great Laments they made, running to the tops of high Hills, and climbing Trees, to send their Eyes after them as far as they could, making Fires, and offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sacrifices, that they might oblige them to return again, and become their Protectors.</p>
               <p>From this Country they sailed to the Islands of <hi>Molacos,</hi> where the Inhabitants in their <hi>Canows,</hi> under Pretence of Trafficking with them, sought to surprize them, but soon found to their Smart, that <hi>Drake</hi> came not to that end; whereupon naming it the <hi>Isle of Thieves,</hi> they stood away to <hi>Tatnate,</hi> where the King of that Country sent his Deputy to intreat them to come on Shoar, whereupon <hi>Drake</hi> cast Anchor, and sent a Messenger to the King with a Scarlet Cloak, desiring that he might be supplyed with Provision, and other Necessaries; who returned Answer by his <hi>Vice-Roy,</hi> that he would do any thing to serve them, and that he would shortly visit them at their Ships, who accordingly came in his <hi>Canow,</hi> attended by several of the Nobility, cloathed in <hi>White Calico.</hi> When as the King did Obeysance in humble manner, being of a tall Stature, Corpulent, and of a Princely Countenance; his Respect amongst his Subjects was very great, none of his Attendants daring to speak to him but on their Knees; he was received on Board with Drums beating, Trumpets sounding, and Vollies of great and small Shot: his Attire from his Wast downwards, was Cloath of Gold, his Legs bare, on his Feet Shooes of <hi>Red Cordivant:</hi> on his Cap were divers Rings of Plated Gold, an Inch and half broad about his Neck, and on his right Hand Rings, set with rich Stones. After he had been treated and welcomed, he returned to Shoar, and sent store of Provision, for which those that brought it, received good Presents: He sent one of his Brothers the next Day, to invite <hi>Drake</hi> to his Palace, but some Suspition arising, by words let fall, he would not go, but sent some of his Gentlemen, detaining the <hi>Vice-Roy</hi> as a Pledge of their safety, who upon their Arrival were honourably received.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60477:11"/> These People are <hi>Moors,</hi> and live in a very plentiful Country, and fertile Clime, but after the <hi>English</hi> had trafficked with them for such Necessaries as they wanted, they, on the 9th of <hi>October</hi> set sail, and arrived at the South of the Island <hi>Caelibes,</hi> where they repaired their Ships, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> there they found Bats as big as Bullets, and Crab-fish that lived on the Land, making holes in the Earth, and running up Trees, and Worms that shined in the Night like Fire. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting from this Island, they sailed to another, but could find no Ground near it at a hundred Fathom, wherefore sailing to the West, <hi>Drake</hi>'s Ship happened to run on a Shole that extended it self seven Leagues, where, had the Wind been high, she had been lost: But Providence so ordered it, by the heaving and setting of the Sea, and the Saylors Endeavours, she got off, and sailing amongst the Islands of the Sea, came at last to <hi>Java,</hi> where the chief King of the Country came on Board, sending before him Store of Provision; him they welcomed in the best sort, with Musick and Provision, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially with Wine, who within a while after, returned highly satisfied: And there having Trafficked a while, they took their leaves, and sailed towards the <hi>Cape of Good Hope;</hi> Coasting along part of <hi>Africa,</hi> they came to the Main of <hi>Rio de Sesto,</hi> and watering in the Mouth of <hi>Tagoine,</hi> passed the <hi>Tropick Cancer,</hi> and stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off to the Sea, on the 26th of <hi>September,</hi> came safe to <hi>Plymouth,</hi> after two Years, ten Months, and some odd Days Absence, bringing with them in Gold, Silver, Jewels, and other Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes, to the Value of 100000 <hi>l.</hi> having incompassed the whole Earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Voyage of Sir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> into the <hi>West-Indies,</hi> wherein are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Town of St. <hi>Domingo,</hi> St. <hi>Jago,</hi> St. <hi>Augustina,</hi> and <hi>Cartage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe <hi>Spaniards</hi> great <hi>Armado,</hi> routed in 88, the Queen to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge the treacherous Design against her Crown and Life, fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out a Fleet consisting of twenty five Sail, on which were Imbar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked 2585 Marriners, and Soldiers, Sir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> being Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, the said Fleet set sail for the <hi>West-Indies,</hi> taking by the way se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Spanish</hi> Vessels, when coming to <hi>Vigo,</hi> they took several <hi>Boats</hi> and <hi>Caravals,</hi> among others, a small Vessel laden with the Furniture of the great Church of St. <hi>Virgo,</hi> in which was much Plate; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60477:12"/> other things, a great Silver Cross double Gilt, all amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Value of 30000 Duckates. In the mean time the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Galicia</hi> came down with three hundred Horse, and two thousand Foot, to defend the shoar, desiring Parley with the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral, promising Water and other Necessaries for Money, which was expected; and after a Supply of all things they required, weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Anchor, and sailed for the <hi>Canaries,</hi> they fell in with <hi>Palma,</hi> with purpose to have landed there: but finding the Shoar strongly fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, changed their purpose, and so sailing by <hi>Faro Cape Blank,</hi> and <hi>Cape Verd,</hi> they came to the Isle of St. <hi>Jago,</hi> and landed 1000 Men, under the Leading of Lieutenaant General of <hi>Carlile;</hi> and marching over Land undiscovered, surprized the Town of St. <hi>Jago,</hi> Situate in a Valley, and planted St. <hi>George</hi>'s Cross upon the Wall, not a Spaniard daring to make Resistance. After which, they marched to St. <hi>Domingo,</hi> and found it abandoned, and although the Treasure was conveyed thence, yet in both places store of Plunder was found, as also in the Town of <hi>Praje;</hi> all Scituate in this pleasant Island, abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with all things necessary for the support of Man.</p>
               <p>The Country thus allarumed, the Spaniards in great numbers run to their Arms, but durst attempt nothing; so that the General com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Praje</hi> to be burnt, which so perplexed the Spaniards, that they resolved to compound for <hi>Domingo,</hi> and St. <hi>Jago;</hi> but whilst the Treaty was in hand, the English had withdrawn themselves out of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingo,</hi> the Spaniards fortifyed it, planting Canons in the Gate, and laying an Ambuscade. Whereupon <hi>Drake</hi>'s 1200 Men went to force the Guard, which accordingly they did, making great slaughter of the Spaniards, so that they fled to the Castle; but Fear so far prevailed with 'em, that they stay'd not long there, but fled; upon which the Town being gained, a <hi>Negro</hi> Boy was sent to such <hi>Spaniards</hi> as were retired to the Mountains, with a Flag of Truce, giving them leave to return in Safety. But as he was going he was run through by a Spaniard, which so enraged the General, that he caused two <hi>Fryers</hi> to be sent to the same place, and there hanged; protesting, that unless the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer was delivered up, he would hang two Prisoners every day, till none was left: Which Pennance so troubled the Spaniards, that they delivered up the Murderer to Justice, who according to his Deserts was executed.</p>
               <p>The Spaniards not coming to Agreement for their City and Town, <hi>Drake</hi> gave order to Fire them, but being most stone Building, it
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60477:12"/> proved a Task very difficult; yet the Spaniards desirous to preserve them, offered 25000 Duccates, which offer was accepted. One thing in the King's House denoting his Ambition, was remarkable, <hi>viz.</hi> An Escutcheon, containing a Globe, and a Horse standing in one part in it, and the other part leaping out of it, with this Motto, <hi>Non sufficiat Orbis, The World is not enough;</hi> which the Spaniards them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves were even ashamed of.</p>
               <p>From this Island they put over to the main Land, and came within sight of <hi>Carthagena,</hi> when landing about four in the Afternoon, Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant General <hi>Carlile</hi> about Mid-night came before the City, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving put a Party of Spanish Horse to flight by the way: Whilst the Vessels on the Road, attacked a small Fort that stood on the Sea Coast. Half a Mile before they came at the City, the Land grew straight, having the Main on the one side, and the Harbour on the other: Which straight was fortifyed with a Wall and a Ditch, only a space left for passage, and on it planted six Pieces of Cannon, that bent upon the said passage. Moreover, the Spaniards had drawn two Gallies into the Harbour, into which, they had put one Ordinance, and 400 small shot, and on the Land-side 300 Men stood armed with Pikes: but the English taking the lower ground, constrained them to flight, and did not Fire till they came up to the Wall, when letting fly a Volly in the Faces of the Spaniards, and seconding it with the Butt-end of their Muskets, they beat them first from their Baracadoes, and secondly, caused them to fly, entering the the Town Pell-mell with them: and obtaining the Market Place planting there a strong Guard, notwithstanding they had Baraca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doed every street, set Indians with Poysoned Arrows at each cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and stuck up poysoned sticks, with sharp points to disable the Soldiers.</p>
               <p>The City thus won, the Joy was not great, by reason of a Mortal Distemper that raged amongst the Soldiers, occasioned by ill Airs, which killed a gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t many of them, and caused some to loose their Wits, which utterly frustrated the Design upon <hi>Nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre de Dios,</hi> and <hi>Panama,</hi> where all the Treasure was. Whilst they lay here, they took two small Spanish Prizes, in attempting which, Captain <hi>Varny,</hi> and Captain <hi>Moon</hi> were slain with Musquet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shot, out of the Bushes where the Spaniards had run their Vessels on shoar.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:60477:13"/>
               <p>The General having given order for the Firing of <hi>Carthagena,</hi> the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, Governour, and some other Principal Men of the Island, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated him to spare it, and they would ransom it at 11000 Duckates, which was accordingly done; and for an Abby that stood some di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance from it, they gave a 1000 Duckates; but refusing to give so much as was demanded for a Castle without the City, it was blown up, so the Army Imbarking, sailed to <hi>Cape</hi> St. <hi>Anthony,</hi> to Water; but sinding none there, passed over to <hi>Florida,</hi> where sailing up the River, they took a Fort of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and found in it several pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Ordnance, and 2000 pounds in Money; and so Coasting along came to <hi>Virginia,</hi> where several <hi>English</hi> resided, under Mr. <hi>Lane</hi> the Governour; to whom <hi>Drake</hi> offered a Ship with Provision; or if they pleased, to transport them into <hi>England,</hi> the latter of which they accepted: not being greatly desirous to stay in a Country where they had found such cold comfort. From this place the whole Fleet set Sail, and arrived safe at <hi>Plymouth,</hi> the 28th of <hi>July;</hi> the Booties got, besides the defraying of Charges, amounted to 6000 pounds, of which the Companies that travelled in the Voyage, were to have 2000 <hi>l.</hi> and their Adventures for their Merchandize, 40000 <hi>l.</hi> In this Voyage, a 150 Men were lost, the great Ordnance taken from the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> were 240 of which 230 were Brass.</p>
               <p>On the 27th of <hi>January</hi> they came to <hi>Villa Porta,</hi> where to the Grief of all <hi>English</hi> Men, the Renowned and truly Worthy Sir <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Drake,</hi> ended his Days, and was set down in a Coffin of Lead in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sea, on which he had so often Triumphed; the Drums beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Cannons sounding at his last Farewel to the World.</p>
               <p>The General being dead, all concluded to return home, which they accordingly did, being forced to fight their way through the <hi>Spanish</hi> Fleet, that was sent to interrupt them, after they had been a Year abroad.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>A Most excellent N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ural Balsam is late brought from <hi>Chili</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> far exceeding that of <hi>Peru</hi> and <hi>Tolu,</hi> in curing most Diseases in Humane Bodies: 'Tis a Remedy no Man under the Sun can compose, as being a most Odoriferous and Natural Balsam. It cures all Pains proceeding from Cold, corroborates the Stomack, creates an Appetite, and strengthens the whole Body: It is a wonderful Remedy for all internal Sores, Bruises, Ʋlcers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and mightily helps all Aythmatical Distempers: 'Tis also a great Cephalick, helping most Diseases of the Head, and strengthning the Brain and Nerves: It kills the Worms, provokes Ʋ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, and is good against the Stone; helps all Fluxes of the Belly, is excellent in all Diseases of the Ears, especially Deafness: I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> also cures all manner of Green Wounds. <hi>Note,</hi> It is only to be had of <hi>E. Tracy,</hi> at the three Bibles on <hi>London-bridge,</hi> at <hi>1 s. 6 d.</hi> the Ounce; the Bottles are all sealed with the Balsam-tree.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>